Guide to the Joseph A. McCarroll papers 2015.001
Brooklyn Historical Society
Joseph A. McCarroll papers
1892-2014
1892-1958
Center for Brooklyn History
McCarroll, Joseph A.
McCarroll, William H.
2015.001
0.25 Linear Feet in fifteen folders
The papers document the life and work of Joseph A. McCarroll, an architect who worked in Brooklyn, Manhattan, Queens, New Jersey, Connecticut, and the West Coast, from around 1907 until 1958. Materials include photographs, architectural renderings, clippings, correspondence, resumes, and one scrapbook. In addition to his work as an architect, the papers also documents McCarroll's interest in amateur astronomy as a member of the Bergen County Amateur Astronomers Association.
Box A0135
Scope and Contents
The papers document the life and work of Joseph A. McCarroll, an architect who worked in Brooklyn, Manhattan, Queens, New Jersey, Connecticut, and the West Coast, from around 1907 until 1958. Materials include photographs, architectural renderings, clippings, correspondence, and one scrapbook. The papers document the construction of various buildings, especially his work on Avenue L, in the Midwood neighborhood of Brooklyn. Other Brooklyn related buildings include apartment buildings in Flatbush, the Meurer Bros. Co. building on Flushing Avenue, the Duryea Presbyterian Church, and the St. Peter Claver Church. His work in Brooklyn primarily dates from 1920 to 1923. Outside of Brooklyn, he worked on the St. Bartholomew's School in Elmhurst, Queens, Jacob Meurer's mansion in Belle Terre, Long Island, and the Postal Life Building in Manhattan. From 1907 to 1909, he worked in California, Seattle, and Vancouver. His work during this time included the Pacific Mutual Life Insurance Company of California building, the Central Building (Sixth and Main Streets), and apartments on South Olive Street, in Los Angeles; the Salinas County Court House; the Sacramento County Court House, City Hall, and Labor Temple, in Sacramento; the Bank of Ottawa and the Bauer Building, in Vancouver; and the Children's Orthopedic Hospital in Seattle. Finally, he also worked on three schools in Connecticut in the 1940s and 1950s.
In addition to his work as an architect, the papers also document McCarroll's interest in amateur astronomy as a member of the Bergen County Amateur Astronomers Association.
The papers also include family portraits, resumes, and professional correspondence. Annotations and clippings added by McCarroll's son, William H. McCarroll, also appear throughout the papers.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William H. McCarroll, 2015.
Biographical note
Joseph Allen McCarroll was born in Brooklyn on September 29, 1873 to William and Jennie Allen McCarroll. His father had emigrated from Ireland around 1870, and became a well known business man and civic activist. Joseph attended Cornell University, graduating in 1895 with a degree in architecture. He then worked in the family leather business for five years, before pursuing a career as an architect. He worked extensively in Brooklyn for 25 years (excepting a three year stint on the West Coast). He ran the McCarroll Construction Company from 1918 to 1925, specializing in residential homes and apartment buildings in Brooklyn. Later he was a principal partner in the firm of McCarroll, Murphy and Lehman, which specialized in the construction of schools and churches. He also worked for the firm of Thomas W. Lamb, which built large movie theaters. Later in life he served as Plan Examiner and Building Inspector for the Township of Teaneck, NJ, and in December 1941 became the Chief Civilian Architect at the United States Submarine Base at Groton, CT. He continued to work as an architect until his retirement in 1958. McCarroll was also an avid amateur astronomer, and was a founding member and President of the Bergen County Amateur Astronomy Association. He died in Lawrenceville, NJ, in October 1970.
Joseph Allen McCarroll was born in Brooklyn, New York, on September 29, 1873 to William and Jennie Allen McCarroll. His father had emigrated from Ireland around 1870, and became a well known business man and civic activist. Joseph attended Cornell University, graduating in 1895 with a degree in architecture. He then worked in the family leather business for five years, before pursuing a career as an architect. He worked extensively in Brooklyn for 25 years (excepting a three year stint on the West Coast). He ran the McCarroll Construction Company from 1918 to 1925, specializing in residential homes and apartment buildings in Brooklyn. Later he was a principal partner in the firm of McCarroll, Murphy and Lehman, which specialized in the construction of schools and churches. He also worked for the firm of Thomas W. Lamb, which built large movie theaters. Later in life he served as Plan Examiner and Building Inspector for the Township of Teaneck, New Jersey, and in December 1941 became the Chief Civilian Architect at the United States Submarine Base at Groton, Connecticut. He continued to work as an architect until his retirement in 1958. McCarroll was also an avid amateur astronomer, and was a founding member and President of the Bergen County Amateur Astronomers Association. He died in Lawrenceville, New Jersey, in October 1970.
Sources
Donor correspondence, 2014
Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Elmhurst (New York, N.Y.); Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Belle Terre (N.Y.); Connecticut; Vancouver (B.C.); Astronomy |z New Jersey; Seattle (Wash.); Architecture |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Photographs; Amateur astronomy |z New Jersey; Clippings (information artifacts); Scrapbooks; Correspondence; Mystic (Conn.); Avenue L (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Sacramento (Calif.); Los Angeles (Calif.); California; Résumés (personnel records); Architects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Midwood (New York, N.Y.); Duryea Presbyterian Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Peter Claver Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Bergen County Amateur Astronomers Association; Meurer Bros. Co. (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); McCarroll, William H.; McCarroll, Joseph A.
- Inventory by William H. McCarroll, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- St. Peter Claver Church and Avenue L development clippings, 1920-1922, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Astronomy, 1931-1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters and resumes, 1908-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Avenue L and other Brooklyn buildings, 1920-1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- New York City - Postal Life Building, 1915, circa 2000s (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Brooklyn, Long Island, and New Jersey renderings and photos, 1912-1923, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Los Angeles renderings, 1907-1908, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Sacramento and Salina County, California renderings, circa 1907-1909 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Seattle and Vancouver renderings, 1909, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- West Coast - Composite of nine buildings, 1907-1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Mystic (CT) area work, 1943-1958 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Search for a Church, 1928, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Biography and family photographs, 1892 - circa 2000s (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Scrapbook, 1912-1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)